This is not a story of Tibet
هذه ليست قصة عن جبال التبت
and it's not a story of the Amazon.
و ليست قصة عن منطقة الأمازون.
I won't be taking you to the high Arctic,
لن تأخذك تلك القصة إلى أعالي القطب الشمالي
the life of the Inuit, or to the searing sands of the Sahara.
ولن تسرد لك عن الحياة في الاسكيمو، أو عن رمال الصحراء الحارقة.
This is actually a story of my own backyard.
في الواقع هي قصة عن منطقة خفية في بلدي
It's a land known to the Tahltan people
أرض معروفة لشعوب تاهلتان
and all the First Nations of British Columbia
ولجميع الشعوب الأولى في كولومبيا البريطانية
as the Sacred Headwaters,
باسم المنابع المقدسة
the source of the three great salmon rivers of home,
إنها منبع ثلاثة أنهار كبيرة تعد موطناً رئيسياً لسمك السلمون
the Skeena, the Stikine and the Nass.
أنهارسكينة و ستيكيني و ناس
It's a valley where, in a long day, perhaps, too,
إنها أحد الأودية حيث يمكنك و عبر يوم طويل
you can follow the tracks of grizzly and wolf
أن تتبع مسارات كل من الدببة والذئاب
and drink from the very sources of water
و أن تشرب من نفس مصدر المياه
that gave rise and cradled the great civilizations
الذي قامت عليه الحضارات العظيمة
of the Northwest Coast.
في الساحل الشمالي الغربي
It's such a beautiful place. It's the most stunningly wild place I've ever been.
إنه مكان جميل. أنه المكان الأكثر إذهالاً الذي رأيته في حياتي
It's the sort of place that we, as Canadians,
إنه مكان يمكننا نحن الكنديين
could throw England, and they'd never find it.
أن نرمي به دولة إنجلترا بأكملها فتضيع فيه تماماً
John Muir, in 1879, went up just the lower third of the Stikine,
جون موير في عام 1879 وصل إلى الثلث الأخير من ستيكيني
and he was so enraptured he called it
و كان سعيداً جداً بهذا الانجاز و أطلق إسم
a Yosemite 150 miles long.
يوسمايت 150 ميل
He came back to California
عندما عاد إلى كاليفورنيا
and named his dog after that river of enchantment.
أسمى كلبه على إسم ذلك النهر الساحر الخلاب
In the Lower 48, the farthest you can get away
في 48 ميل الأخيرة أقصى ما يمكنك الوصول إليه
from a maintained road is 20 miles.
بعد أن تترجل عن الطريق الأسفلتي هي مسافة 20 ميل
In the Northwest Quadrant of British Columbia,
في شمال غرب كولومبيا البريطانية
an area of land the size of Oregon, there's one road,
مساحة الأرض هناك تعادل حجم ولاية أوريغون و هناك طريق واحد
a narrow ribbon of asphalt that slips up the side
ضيق من الأسفلت يتعرج
of the Coast Mountains to the Yukon.
من جبال الساحل إلى يوكون.
I followed that road in the early 1970s,
لقد تتبعت هذا الطريق في أوائل السبعينات
soon after it was built, to take a job as the first park ranger
بعد أن رُصِفت بوقت قصير فقد كنت أول حارس غابات هناك
in Spatsizi wilderness.
في برية سباتسيزي
My job description was deliciously vague:
وكان وصف وظيفتي لذيذ غامض
wilderness assessment and public relations.
كانت تدعى " تقييم البرية والعلاقات العامة "
In two four-month seasons I saw not a dozen people.
خلال موسمين مدة كل موسم أربعة أشهر لم أرى أكثر من عشرة أشخاص
There was no one to relate publicly to.
لم يكن هناك أحد لتوطد معه العلاقات العامة
But in the course of these wanderings,
ولكن أثناء هذا التيه في تلك العجائب
I came upon an old shaman's grave
وجدت قبر الشامان القديم
that led to an encounter with a remarkable man:
و الذي خولني أن أتعرف على رجل مميز
Alex Jack, an Gitxsan elder and chief who had lived
يدعى أليكس جاك أكبر زعيم ضمن قبائل جيتكسسان
as a trapper and a hunter in that country for all of his life.
و قد عاش كصياد و صانع فخاخ طيلة حياته
And over the course of 30 years, I recorded traditional tales
وعلى مدى الـ30 عاماً التي مضت سجلت كل القصص الأسطورية
from Alex, mostly mythological accounts of Wy-ghet,
التي أخبرني بها أليكس ، معظمهما قصص أسطورية عن ايومينج-غيت
the trickster transformer of Gitxsan lore
محتال متحول من قبائل "لور جيتكسسان"
who, in his folly, taught the people how to live on the land.
و الذي و بحمقه علم الناس كيف تعيش في هذه الأرض
And just before Alex died at the age of 96,
و قبل فترة قصيرة من وفاة أليكس في سن ال 96
he gave me a gift.
قدم لي هدية
It was a tool carved from caribou bone
كانت أداة منحوتة من عظم الكاريبو
by his grandfather in 1910,
نحتت بواسطة جده في عام 1910
and it turned out to be a specialized implement
واتضح أن نحتت لكي تكون متخصصة
used by a trapper to skin out the eyelids of wolves.
لإستخدام الصياد في سلخ جفون الذئاب
It was only when Alex passed away that I realized that
عندما رحل أليكس فحسب أدركت أن
the eyelids, in some sense, were my own,
الجفون - بمعنى ما - كانت جفوني أنا
and having done so much to allow me to learn to see,
تلك الهدية بعد فترة طويلة من الزمن علمتني كيف أرى
Alex in his own way was saying goodbye.
أليكس كان يقول لي وداعا بطريقته الخاصة
Well, isolation has been the great saving grace
حسنا، عزلة تلك المنطقة كانت النعمة الأكبر
of this remarkable place, but today isolation could be its doom.
لهذا المكان الرائع، ولكن العزلة اليوم يمكن أن تكون النقمة الأكبر !
You've heard so much about the developments of the tar sands,
قد سمعتم الكثير عن التطورات التي حدثت في مجال رمال القطران
the controversy about the Keystone and the Enbridge pipelines,
و الجدل حول حجر الأساس لخطوط أنابيب انبريدجي
but these are just elements of a tsunami
ولكن هذه عناصر فقط من تسونامي
of industrial development that is sweeping across
تنمية صناعية سوف تجتاح كل أنحاء
all of the wild country of northern Canada.
تلك المنطقة البرية في شمال كندا
In Tahltan territory alone, there are 41 major industrial proposals,
في إقليم تاهلتان وحده، هناك 41 مقترح صناعي رئيسي
some with great promise, some of great concern.
بعضها يحمل الأمل العظيم و لكن الآخر ينطوي عليه قلق عظيم أيضاً
On Todagin Mountain,
فيما يخص جبال توداجين
revered by the Tahltan people as a wildlife sanctuary in the sky,
جبل حافظ عليه شعب تاهلتان كملاذ للحياة البرية في السماء،
home to the largest population of stone sheep on the planet,
موطن أكبر عدد من السكان من الأغنام الحجرية على هذا الكوكب
Imperial Metals --
شركة المعادن الإمبراطورية
but the 75th-biggest mining company in all of Canada --
واحدة من أكبر شركات التعدين في كندا
has secured permits to establish an open-pit
حصل على تصريح إقامة حفرة مفتوحة
copper and gold mine which will process
لكي تستخدم كمنجم لألنحاس والذهب التي سوف تقوم باستخراج
30,000 tons of rock a day for 30 years,
30 ألف طن من الصخور يومياً لمدة 30 عاماً
generating hundreds of millions of tons of toxic waste
وتولد مئات الملايين من الأطنان من النفايات السامة
that, by the project's design, will simply be dumped
و التي و بحسب تصميم المشروع سوف يتم اغراقها ببساطة
into the lakes of the Sacred Headwaters.
في منطقة بحيرات " المنابع المقدسة "
At the Headwaters itself,
و في لب المنابع ذاتها
Shell Canada has plans to extract methane gas
شركة "شل كندا" لديها خطط لاستخراج غاز الميثان
from coal seams that underly a million acres,
من طبقات الفحم التي تنبسط على مدى مليون فدان
fracking the coal with hundreds of millions of gallons
و تكسير الفحم ذاك سوف ينتج بالموازاة مئات ملايين الغالونات
of toxic chemicals,
من المواد الكيميائية السامة
establishing perhaps as many as 6,000 wellheads,
حيث من المخطط إنشاء ربما ما يصل إلى 6,000 عين بئر
and eventually a network of roads and pipelines
و فوق كل هذا سيتم إنشاء شبكة من الطرق وخطوط الأنابيب
and flaring wellheads, all to generate methane gas
و سوف تشتعل عيون الآبار كل هذا لتوليد غاز الميثان
that most likely will go east
و الذي سوف يتم نقله على الارجح نحو الشرق
to fuel the expansion of the tar sands.
لإمداد مشاريح رمال القطران بالطاقة
For over a decade, the Tahltan people,
لأكثر من عقد .. شعب تاهلتان
both clans, Wolf and Crow,
بكل العشائر، كعشيرة الذئب وعشيرة الغراب،
have resisted this assault on their homeland.
قاوموا هذا الاعتداء على وطنهم.
Men, women and children of all ages,
حيث سد الرجال والنساء والأطفال من جميع الإعمار،
elders in wheelchairs, have blockaded
وحتى الشيوخ على كراسيهم المتحركة أغلقوا
the only road access to the interior.
الطريق الوحيد الذي يخول الوصول إلى المناطق الداخلية هناك
For them, the Headwaters is a kitchen.
بالنسبة لهم المنابع مطبخ ..
It's a sanctuary. It's a burial ground of their ancestors.
ملاذ و أرض لدفن الأجداد
And those who really own it
و من يملك تلك الأراضي حقاً
are the generations as yet unborn.
هي الأجيال التي لم تولد بعد
The Tahltan have been able,
استطاعت شعوب تاهلتان
with the support of all Canadians who live downstream,
بالدعم من جميع الكنديين الذين يعيشون في اتجاه مجرى النهر
all local politicians, to resist this assault on their homeland,
و بدعم من جميع السياسيين المحليين مقاومة هذا الاعتداء في وطنهم
but now everything hangs in the balance.
ولكن اليوم تساوت كفة القوى فيما بينهم
Decisions that will be made this year will literally determine
و القررات التي سوف تصدر هذا العام سوف تحدد " حرفياً "
the fate of this country.
مصير هذا البلد.
The Tahltan have called for the creation
لقد دعت شعوب تاهلتان
of a tribal heritage reserve which will set aside
إلى أنشاء منطقة محمية للتراث قبلي لكي تؤسس بالقرب
the largest protected area in British Columbia.
من أكبر منطقة محمية في كولومبيا البريطانية.
Our goal is not only to help them do that
أن هدفنا ليس لمساعدتهم على القيام بذلك فقط
but to encourage our friends, the good people at Shell,
ولكن هدفنا تشجيع أصدقائنا - الناس الطيبين في شركة شل كندا -
not only to withdraw from the Sacred Headwaters,
ليس على الانسحاب من "المنابع المقدسة" فقط
but to move forward with us and join us
ولكن على المضي قدما معنا والانضمام إلينا
as we do the remarkable, the extraordinary:
في حفظ هذا التراث الفريد والخلاب
set aside a protected area that will be for all time
عن طريق تخصيص منطقة محمية هناك إلى الأبد
not simply the Sacred Headwaters of the Tahltan people
و ببساطة لا أن يحموا "المنابع المقدسة" لشعب تاهلتان فقط
but the sacred headwaters of all people in the world.
بل كل المنابع المقدسة لجميع الناس في كل انحاء العالم.
The Tahltan need your help. We need your help.
شعب تاهلتان بحاجة لمساعدتكم ونحن بحاجة إلى مساعدتكم
And if any of you would like to join us on this great adventure,
و ان كان منكم من يريد ان ينضم إلى هذه المغامرة الشيقة
please come and see me later today.
أرجو أن يأتي و يحدثني اليوم لاحقاً في هذا الخصوص
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)